Chapter 1. Introduction

If you’re expecting a run-of-the-mill best practices manual, be aware that there’s an ulterior message that will be running through this one. While the primary goal is certainly to give you the information you need to create accessible EPUB 3 publications, it also seeks to address the question of why you need to pay attention to the quality of your data, and how accessible data and general good data practices are more tightly entwined than you might think.

Accessibility is not a feel-good consideration that can be deferred to republishers to fill in for you as you focus on print and quick-and-dirty ebooks, but a content imperative vital to your survival in the digital future, as I’ll take the odd detour from the planned route to point out. Your data matters, not just its presentation, and the more you see the value in it the more sense it will make to build in accessibility from the ground up.

It’s a common misconception, for example, that any kind of data is accessible data, and that assistive technologies like screen readers work magic and absolve you of paying attention to what’s going on “under the hood,” so to speak. Getting the message out early that this is not the case is essential to making EPUB more than just a minimally accessible format and preventing past mistakes from being perpetuated.

It’s unfortunately too easy when moving from a visual medium like print to treat digital content as nothing more than yet another display medium, however. The simple path is to graft what you know onto what you don’t. But it’s that thinking that perpetuates the inaccessibility of content. Everything starts with the source. All the bells and whistles your reading system can do for you to assist in rendering and playback ultimately rely on the value of the content underneath and the ability to make sense of it.

Treat your data as a second-class citizen and eventually you’ll be recognized as a second-class publisher.

But try and turn your brain off to the word accessibility as you read this guide and focus instead on the need to create rich, flexible, and versatile content that can make the reading experience better for everyone.

Inaccessible content typically means you’re settling for the least value you can get, so get ready to think bigger.

The Digital Famine

Before getting into the best practices themselves, there are two subjects that it would be a lapse for me to not talk about first. The digital famine is the first, as it will hopefully give you some real-world perspective on why accessibility matters.

You’re probably wondering what the famine is, since there are some impressive statistics emerging to show that the ebook revolution isn’t slowing down any time soon. Unfortunately, the numbers aren’t where it matters most yet if you believe in universal access to information. Sales are rising exponentially year over year, but the number of accessible ebooks available at the source is still small.

A commonly cited statistic in accessibility circles is that only about 5 percent of the books produced in any year are ever made available in an accessible format. Although there are signs that this rate is beginning to tick upward with more ebooks being produced, the overall percentage of books that become available in accessible formats still remains abysmally small. Fiction bestsellers are a bright spot, as they’ve been the first to receive the digital treatment, but there’s more to reading than just fiction.

Picture yourself in the situation where you’ll only ever have a spattering of books at your fingertips in any given subject area, and probably none in the more niche topics you delve into. It’s not a matter of finding another bookstore or reading application; those books just aren’t coming and there’s nothing you can do to change it. This dearth of content is what people refer to as the digital famine.

Not a pleasant thought, and it’s a reality that many people are forced to live right now; it’s only imaginary if you’re fortunate not to be affected. The ebook revolution holds out the promise of improvement, as mainstream publishing finds itself suddenly charting the same path as accessible producers, but there are still a number of factors that will contribute to this paltry number for some time to come, including:

New workflows haven’t yet emerged to facilitate the transition. Mass retail ebook production and consumption took many people by surprise, the author included, after earlier failed attempts. Tools and production systems are not optimized for high-quality multi-stream output production, making internal conversion of print to digital costly.

Accessible ebooks can become inaccessible after ingestion into a distribution channel, whether via reformatting to less feature-rich formats or for feature-reduced reading.

The inaccessibility of online bookstores themselves can hinder the ability to obtain ebooks.

Libraries for the blind and other republishers don’t have the resources to completely re-engineer the print-only books still being produced. And this model is a failing one for the long-term ideal of full content accessibility.

But, while depressing in the short term, none of these issues are insurmountable, and none are antithetical to producing good content. It’s only to say that there are interesting times ahead, and to reinforce that there remains much still to be done. The existence of EPUB 3 alone does not cure this famine.

Accessibility and Usability

The other subject that needs treatment is what is meant by accessibility and usability in the context of this guide. These two terms are often used in overlapping fashion, and can mean different things to different people, but I’ll be using the following definitions:

Accessibility of content is the intrinsic capabilities of the EPUB 3 publication: the quality of the data and meaning that can be extracted from it; the built-in navigational capabilities; the additional functionality, like text and audio synchronization (media overlays) and improved synthetic speech. The publisher of an EPUB has control over the accessibility of their publication, whether directly through the tools they use to generate the source or in post-production workflows.

Usability is the ability of a reader to access the content on any given reading system. A publisher may make an EPUB 3 publication rich with accessibility features, but if a reader does not have the right device or software program to access those features it is not the publication itself that is to blame.

But even making these distinctions, there’s no simple answer to what a fully accessible EPUB is, or to what a completely usable reading system is. It means something different depending on your needs.

A person with a print disability, for example, “cannot effectively read print because of a visual, physical, perceptual, developmental, cognitive, or learning disability” (DAISY Glossary). The best method to address any one of these areas is not necessarily the best method to address any of the others. Audio is necessary for readers who are blind, for example, but a reader who is dyslexic might benefit from audio, or from font changes or visual cues, or from a combination of these. There’s no universal answer.

And with EPUB 3 opening the door to new rich multimedia experiences, so too do you need to think beyond traditional print disabilities and recognize that ebooks have the potential to exclude a greater segment of the population if not done with care:

the inability to hear embedded audio and video is a concern for persons who are deaf or hard or hearing;

interactivity and animations that rely on color recognition have the potential to exclude persons who are color blind or have difficulty distinguishing blended contrasts;

the new trend to voice activated devices has the potential to make reading for persons with speech impairments difficult.

The point isn’t to suggest that the problem is too big to try and tackle, in fact the opposite. If you haven’t caught on, I’m making the case why ignoring accessibility means ignoring a large segment of readers who would love to be buying and consuming your ebooks. It is estimated that 10 percent of the population has a print disability; that’s a large market you could be catering to to increase your sales.

And we haven’t yet touched on situational disabilities. A situational disability is one in which a person who would otherwise be able to interact with your ebook is in a position in which they can’t, or find themselves facing the same limitations. For example:

someone trying to read on a cell phone will gain an appreciation for the difficulty of reading small sections of prose at a time, as someone with low vision experiences when reading using zooming software;

someone attempting to read on their deck on a bright summer day, angling and holding their tablet close to their face to follow the prose, will understand the difficulty experienced by someone with age-related sight loss and/or who has trouble with contrasts;

someone sitting on the subway going home who has to turn on subtitles in an embedded video to read the dialogue will experience how a person who is deaf interacts with the video.

In other words, everyone will benefit from accessible data at some point in their lives, as there are a lot of ways accessible data improves access that aren’t always immediately obvious. Accessibility is critical for some and universally beneficial for all.

The richer you make your data the more intelligently it can be used; so even though you may not be able to accommodate everyone at the end of the day, you can go a long way toward accommodating the majority with a number of simple measures. And that is the focus of this guide.

Usability as defined here, however, is outside the realm of content production, and can’t be tackled by a guide whose focus is increasing the quality of your content. The EPUB specification bakes in some requirements on the reading system side to improve usability, but not every reading system is going to support every accessible feature, and usability is not just support for EPUB but extends into the design of reading systems themselves.

You can’t let usability influence your accessibility decision making, however. A typical practice is to target the industry-leading platform and build around its capabilities (and deficiencies), but what value does this bring you in the long term? Think of the cost that resulted from making Internet Explorer-only friendly websites when it held 90 plus percent of the market as an example of where following the leader can take you. Your books will hopefully be selling well for years to come, but unless you enjoy reformatting from scratch each time you look to upgrade or enhance, it pays to put the effort into doing them right up front.

But it’s time to roll up our sleeves and get our hands dirty…

The Untold Story: Metadata

Bringing up the topic of metadata usually triggers thoughts about the need to include title and author information in an ebook. While certainly a necessity, this kind of traditional metadata is not what we’re going to delve into now.

One of the big issues facing people with disabilities as they try to enter the ebook market is how to discover the quality of the ebooks they want to buy. One ebook is not the same as another, as we’ve been discussing, and readers need to know what they’re getting when they pay for your product. And you should be rewarded for your commitment to accessibility by having your ebooks stand out from the crowd.

Unfortunately, in the past, once you pushed your ebook into a distribution channel, whatever good work you had done to make your content accessible would become indistinguishable from all the inaccessible content out there to the person on the purchasing end. At about the same time that EPUB 3 was being finalized, however, the people at EDItEUR introduced a new set of accessibility metadata for use in ONIX records. This metadata plugs the information gap.

Note

This guide can’t possibly explain all of ONIX, nor would it be the appropriate place to do so. If you are not familiar with the standard, please visit the EDItEUR Web site for more information.

An ONIX record, if you’re not familiar, is an industry-standard message (xml record) that accompanies your publication, providing distributors with both content and distribution metadata. This information is typically used to market and sell your ebook, and these new properties now allow you to enhance that information with the accessible features your ebook includes. Retailers can then make this information available in the product description, for example, so readers can determine whether the ebook will adequately meet their needs. It’s also not a stretch to imagine this information being integrated into bookstore search engines to allow readers to narrow their results based on their needs.

To include accessibility metadata in your ONIX record, you use the ProductFormFeature element, which is described in the standard as a composite container for product information (e.g., it is also used to provide product safety information). To identify that the element contains accessibility information, it must include a ProductFormFeatureType child element with the value 09, as in the following example:

<ProductFormFeature>
    <ProductFormFeatureType>09</ProductFormFeatureType>
    …
</ProductFormFeature>

When this value is encountered, it indicates that the value of the sibling ProductFormFeatureValue element is drawn from ONIX for Books codelist 196, which defines the new accessible properties and the values to use in identifying them. As of writing, this codelist includes the following properties:

No reading system accessibility options disabled (10)

Table of contents navigation (11)

Index navigation (12)

Reading order (13)

Short alternative descriptions (14)

Full alternative descriptions (15)

Visualised data also available as non-graphical data (16)

Accessible math content (17)

Accessible chem content (18)

Print-equivalent page numbering (19)

Synchronised pre-recorded audio (20)

So, for example, if our EPUB contains accessible math formulas (using MathML) we would indicate it as follows:

<ProductFormFeature>
    <ProductFormFeatureType>09</ProductFormFeatureType>
    <ProductFormFeatureValue>17</ProductFormFeatureValue>
</ProductFormFeature>

Likewise, to indicate accessible chemistry content (using ChemML) we would use the value 18:

<ProductFormFeature>
    <ProductFormFeatureType>09</ProductFormFeatureType>
    <ProductFormFeatureValue>18</ProductFormFeatureValue>
</ProductFormFeature>

You must repeat the ProductFormFeature element for each accessibility requirement your EPUB meets; it is not valid to combine all your features into a single element.

You must also ensure that you make yourself familiar with the requirements for compliance before adding any accessibility properties; each of the properties defined in codelist 196 includes conformance criteria. EPUB requires table of contents navigation, for example, but the addition of the required navigation document does not automatically indicate compliance. You need to include full navigation, plus navigation to any tables and figures, before you comply with the table of contents navigation requirement. Likewise, all EPUBs have a reading order defined by the spine element in the package document, but that does not mean you comply to including a reading order. You need to ensure that sidebars and footnotes and similar information has been properly marked up so as not to interfere with the narrative flow, as we went over in the section on the logical reading order.

It is additionally worth noting that there are three properties that aren’t directly related to the content of your EPUB:

Compatibility tested (97)

Trusted intermediary contact (98)

Publisher contact for further accessibility information (99)

Each of these properties requires the addition of a child ProductFormFeatureDescription element to describe compliance:

<ProductFormFeature>
    <ProductFormFeatureType>09</ProductFormFeatureType>
    <ProductFormFeatureValue>97</ProductFormFeatureValue>
    <ProductFormFeatureDescription>
        Content has been tested to work on iBooks, Sony Reader and Adobe Digital
        Editions in both scripting enabled and disabled modes.
    </ProductFormFeatureDescription>
</ProductFormFeature>

Whatever compatibility testing you’ve performed should be listed using code 97 so that readers can better determine the suitability of your ebook for their purposes. Not all reading systems and assistive technologies work alike, or interact well together, and real-world testing is the only way to tell what does and does not work.

There are organizations who specialize in testing across a broad spectrum of devices who can assist you in evaluating your content, as this kind of evaluation can be no small undertaking. A good practice to develop, for example, might be to periodically have typical examples of content coming out of your production stream tested for compatibility issues. The resulting statement could then be re-used across much of your content, so long as the features and markup used remain consistent.

Once you start getting creative with your content (e.g., using extensive scripted interactivity), you should engage experts as early on in the process as you can to ensure any statement you make remains true, however.

The other two codes provide contact information for the person(s) in your organization, or at a trusted intermediary, who can provide additional accessibility information:

<ProductFormFeature>
    <ProductFormFeatureType>09</ProductFormFeatureType>
    <ProductFormFeatureValue>99</ProductFormFeatureValue>
    <ProductFormFeatureDescription>
        accessibility-officer@example.com
    </ProductFormFeatureDescription>
</ProductFormFeature>

If you’re providing educational materials, for example, you’ll want to provide educators a way to be able to contact you to determine whether your content will be accessible by students with various needs that may not be specifically addressed in your compatibility testing statement or in the available metadata properties.

The Coded Word: Scripted Interactivity

Whether you’re a fan of scripted ebooks or not, EPUB 3 has opened the door to their creation, so we’ll now take a look at some of the potential accessibility pitfalls and how they can be avoided.

One of the key new terms you’ll hear in relation to the use of scripting in EPUB 3 is progressive enhancement. The concept of progressive enhancement is not original to EPUB, however, nor is it limited to scripting. I’ve actually been making a case for many of its other core tenets throughout this guide, such as separation of content and style, content conveying meaning, etc. Applied in this context, however, it means that scripting must only enhance your core content.

We’ve already covered why structure and semantics should carry all the information necessary to understand your content, but that presupposes that it is all available. The ability for scripts to remove access to content from anyone without a JavaScript-enabled reading system is a major concern not just for persons using accessible devices, but for all readers.

And that’s why scripting access to content is forbidden in EPUB 3. If you try to circumvent the specification requirement and treat progressive enhancement as just an “accessibility thing,” you’re underestimating the readership that are going to rely on your content rendering properly without scripting. Picture buying a book that has pages glued together and you’ll get an idea of how excited your readers will be that you thought no one would notice.

Note

Note that it’s not a truism that you can expect JavaScript support in EPUB 3 reading systems. There will undoubtedly be widespread support for scripting in time, but support is an optional feature that vendors and developers can choose to ignore.

Meeting the general requirement to keep your text accessible is really not asking a lot, though. As soon as you turn to JavaScript to alter (or enable) access to prose, you should realize you’re on the wrong path. To this end:

Don’t include content that can only be accessed (made visible) through scripted interaction.

Don’t script-enable content based on a reader’s preferences, location, language, or any other setting.

Don’t require scripting in order for the reader to continue moving through the content (e.g., choose your own adventure books).

Whether or not your prose can be accessed is not hard to test, even if it can’t be done reliably by validators like epubcheck. Turn off JavaScript and see if you can navigate your document from beginning to end. You may not get all the bells and whistles when scripting is turned off, but you should be able to get through with no loss of information. If you can’t, you need to review why prose is not available or has disappeared, why navigation gets blocked, etc., and find another way to do what you were attempting.

Don’t worry that this requirement means all the potential scripting fun is being taken out of ebooks, though. Games and puzzles and animations and quizzes and any other secondary content you can think of that requires scripting are all fair game for inclusion. But when it comes to including these there are two considerations to make, very similar to choosing when to describe images:

Does the scripted content you’re embedding include information that will be useful to the reader’s comprehension (demos, etc.), or is it included purely for pleasure (games)?

Can the content be made accessible in a usable way and can you provide a fallback alternative that provides the same or similar experience?

The answer to the first question will have some influence how you tackle the second. If the scripted content provides information that the reader would otherwise not be able to obtain from the prose, you should consider other alternative forms for making that information available, for example:

If you script an interactive demo using the canvas element, consider also providing a transcript of the information for readers who may not be able to interact with it.

If you’re including an interactive form that automatically evaluates the reader’s responses, also include access to an answer key.

If you’re adding a problem or puzzle to solve, also provide the solution so the reader can still learn the steps to its completion.

None of the above suggestions are intended to remove the responsibility to try and make the content accessible in the first place, though. Scripting of accessible forms, for example, should be a trivial task for developers familiar with WAI-ARIA (we’ll look at some practices in the coming section). But trivial or not, because scripting will not necessarily be available, it’s imperative that you provide other means for readers to obtain the full experience.

If the scripted content is purely for entertainment purposes, however, create a fallback commensurate with the value of that content to the overall ebook (if it absolutely cannot be made accessible natively). Like decorative images, a reader unable to interact with non-essential content is not going to be hugely interested in reading a five-page dissertation on each level of your game. A simple idea of what it does will usually suffice.

A Blank Slate: Canvas

Another anticipated use for scripting is to automate the new HTML5 canvas element. This element provides an automatable surface for drawing on, whether it’s done by the content creator (games, animations, etc.) or the reader (drawing or writing surface), which is why I omitted tackling it with the rest of the semantics and structure elements.

Although a potentially interesting element to use in ebooks, at this time the canvas element remains largely a black hole to assistive technologies. A summary of the discussions that have been taking place to fix the accessibility problems as of writing is available on the Paciello Group website. Fixes for these accessibility issues will undoubtedly come in time, perhaps directly for the element or perhaps through WAI-ARIA, but it’s too soon to say.

So is the answer to avoid the element completely until the problems are solved? It would be nice if you could, but wouldn’t be realistic to expect of everyone. Using it judiciously would be a better course to steer.

For now including accessible alternatives is about all you can do. If you’re using the element to draw graphs and charts, you could add a description with the data using the aria-describedby attribute and the techniques we outlined while dealing with images. If you’re using the element for games and the like, consider the issues we detailed at the outset of the section in determining how much information to give.

With canvas, we really have to wait and see, unfortunately.

Using Code Examples

This book is here to help you get your job done. In general, you may use the code in this book in your programs and documentation. You do not need to contact us for permission unless you’re reproducing a significant portion of the code. For example, writing a program that uses several chunks of code from this book does not require permission. Selling or distributing a CD-ROM of examples from O’Reilly books does require permission. Answering a question by citing this book and quoting example code does not require permission. Incorporating a significant amount of example code from this book into your product’s documentation does require permission.

We appreciate, but do not require, attribution. An attribution usually includes the title, author, publisher, and ISBN. For example: “Accessible EPUB 3 by Matt Garrish (O’Reilly). Copyright 2012 Matt Garrish, 9781449328030.”

If you feel your use of code examples falls outside fair use or the permission given above, feel free to contact us at permissions@oreilly.com.

Accessible EPUB 3

Matt Garrish

Editor

Brian Sawyer

Editor

Dan Fauxsmith

Copyright © 2012 O’Reilly Media, Inc

O’Reilly books may be purchased for educational, business, or sales promotional use. Online editions are also available for most titles (http://my.safaribooksonline.com). For more information, contact our corporate/institutional sales department: (800) 998-9938 or corporate@oreilly.com.

Nutshell Handbook, the Nutshell Handbook logo, and the O’Reilly logo are registered trademarks of O’Reilly Media, Inc. Accessible EPUB 3 and related trade dress are trademarks of O’Reilly Media, Inc.

Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers to distinguish their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those designations appear in this book, and O’Reilly Media, Inc. was aware of a trademark claim, the designations have been printed in caps or initial caps.

While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this book, the publisher and authors assume no responsibility for errors or omissions, or for damages resulting from the use of the information contained herein.

O’Reilly Media, Inc. 1005 Gravenstein Highway North Sebastopol CA 95472